<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tvvo notorious murders one committed by a tanner on his wiues sonne nere Horne-church in Essex, the other on a grasier nere Ailsburie in Buckinghamshire : with these is intermixt another murdrous intending fellonie at Rislip in Middlesex, all done this last month.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07918</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18289</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2243</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23188985</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23188985</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26357</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07918)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26357)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1800:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tvvo notorious murders one committed by a tanner on his wiues sonne nere Horne-church in Essex, the other on a grasier nere Ailsburie in Buckinghamshire : with these is intermixt another murdrous intending fellonie at Rislip in Middlesex, all done this last month.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Blackwall, &amp; George Shaw, and are to be sold ouer against Guild-hall gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1595]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint date suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>T.p. contains woodcut ill.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with loss of imprint date and signatures.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Murder --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26357:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26357:1"/>
            <p>Tvvo notorious Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. One committed by a Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner on his wiues ſonne, nere Horne-church in Eſſex.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The other on a Graſier nere Ailsburie in</hi> Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamſhire. With theſe is intermixt another murdrous intending fellonie at Riſlip in Middleſex. All done this laſt month.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of hanged man</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for William Blackwall, &amp; George Shaw: and are to be ſold ouer againſt Guild-hall gate.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26357:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26357:2"/>
            <head>Three cruell felonies and two hated murders performed this laſt moneth by the father and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in law againſt the Sun and brother, the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>againſt the neighbours child, the falſe fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar againſt his vnmiſdeeming freend.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Irdes obſerue ſeaſons, Beaſt knowe the courſe of tymes, eyther to their owne kind are kind: but men neither regard time, nor make vſe of example but with a headlong fury follow their owne appetite. Experience in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hath approued that Sin hath not béen in the higheſt Eſtate vnpuniſhed eſpecially that ſinne, that is to nature abhorting, before good men moſt deteſtable, of God from the beginning deteſted. Murder, I meane, that crying ſinne, that ſinne which gaue the firſt murderer horror of heart, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents all his ſucceſſors, with hell of conſcience. Of ſo many thouſand bloodthirſtie tirants, cloſe plotting poyſoners, felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious waiting murderes, let any man tel me, which went vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his graue in peace? the ſcripture, prophane Stories, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords and cronicles of all nations, remember not one, but all point out a miſerable, ſudden and certaine ruine to him that lay in wait for blood. The wiſedome of our fathers in elder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the policie of maieſtrates in theſe times, wherein iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie rageth, by puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t haue ſought to warne the liuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toucht to remember the guilty put to death, that they may feare to fall into ſuch miſfortune. To this they thought good to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> publiſhing of their deteſted crimes, that thoſe whoſe eyes could not behold their deſerued endes, might yet by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be warned. The imitation whereof wee follow, and in as few wordes as the matter wil giue leaue deſcribe thrée ſorrowful accidents, gathered from the confeſſion of the male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors.</p>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:26357:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The murder of Thomas Chambers.</head>
               <p>In Eſſex not farre from London in the pariſh of vp maſter, at a place called Corbetts Tie, dwelt on Iohn wright, who had married the widdow of one Chambers a Tanner: whoſe Sonne Thomas Chambers being a yong man of great to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes, of condition gentle, of body well proportioned, was bereft of life euen when he began to liue, by the conſpiracie of his vnkinde brother in law Iohn Graygooſe of Epping huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, that had maried Chambers ſiſter, &amp; Iohn Wrights cruelty the vnnaturall huſband of his mother. The cauſe that mooued theſe two this ſinne to attempt, aroſe from hence Thomas Chambers being by his father left heire to 30. <abbr>l.</abbr> a yeare, and a portion of 200. <abbr>l</abbr> and vpwards in money, which money and land at chriſtmas next was to come to his hande, or if he died vnder age a great part of it, then to fall vnto the wife of the aboue named Graygooſe: Graygooſe (as at his death Wright proteſted) about Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dlemas laſt came vnto him and plotted murder, promiſing the benefit that by Chambers death to either of them might ariſe. O falſe temptation of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing gaine: how blind are men to be ſo abuſed? how fond to fall ſo fondly? to beléeue the deuill ſo quickly? when they can no ſooner haue perfected ſo odious an ill, but vengeance like a théefe in the night ſeazeth on them: nay like a violent tempeſt beates downe their violence. But to our matter. Graygooſe was the wicked tempter, Wright as willingly tempted, the one conceiues the miſchéefe, the other conſentes: many times they méeteplott, conſpire, &amp; in the end conclude, that about Epping or Wéeldſide in Eſſex, in one of the Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon holidaies he ſhould be ſlaine: which of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could firſt méete him promiſed to be the murderer. So part theſe vile conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, eyther attending the diſmall time of Chambers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Wright being alwaies in the houſe, had fitter op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity than his confederate, and on the ſixt of Iune before the appointed time, knowing Thomas Chambers to be forth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26357:3"/>
betwéene the howers of ten and twelue awaited at a place called Ruſhy gréene nere Barrow hill, in the pariſh of horne-church, and with a ſtake taken out of a ſtyle he there aſſaulted the vnmiſtruſting yong man, &amp; at one blow giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on the right ſide of his head ſtroke out his braines: which done dragd him into a buſh, and there hid the murdred body: and with a bold face returned home. The youth being well beloued was in ſundry places ſought for, and no ſmall ſuſpition of his murder had by thoſe of good conceipt. At length on whitſon munday being the ix. of Iune a gray-hound found the murdred body, and neuer left baying till it was drawne forth. Oh wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed eſtate of blood guilty murderers, how often haue the foules in the ayre wonderfully bewraied your long concealed acts, how often haue bruite beaſtes wondered at you? howe often haue your trecherous hearts betrayed you? Though men ſee yée not God doth? though men bewray yée not, birds may? yf birdes doo not, beaſtes may, if neither doo, your own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ſhall, but if they be ſeared vp, God certainly wil find out a meane.</p>
               <p>When Chambers body was thus found, a rufull ſight it was to looke vpon, his faire countenance was diſcoulored, wormes cralled in his mouth, noſe, eares, and his whole body was putrefied. The miſſing of Wright that euening the deed was done, ſome ſuſpitious wordes, but chéefely Gods will made Wright to be ſuſpected: and albeit, at the firſt he ſought to face it out, yet before a Iuſtice he confeſſed it preſently, in manner as is before recited: for which hee worthely ſuffered death on Munday the 14. of Iuly at Rumforde in Eſſex, and Graygooſe is to abide his triall at Chelmeſford. O that all ſtepfathers and mothers might poſſibly haue heard Wrights lamentation, how he exhorted them to beware, how he exclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on coueteouſnes, how he deſired forgiuenes, they woulde then remember the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that were orphanes committed to their patronage, were to be vſed as derely as their naturall children, but it ſéemed he knew his duity and forget it; and if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he not (as he was) giuen ouer, they will remember it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:26357:4"/>
               <head>The robbery of Pets houſe with the wounding of his ſonne.</head>
               <p>OVr Second ſeene of this thréefold tragedy, was acted in Riſlip a country towne in Middleſex. Two neighbors dwelt in that pariſh, Murdox the one an honeſt wealthy Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Pets the other a carpenter though not rich, yet of honeſt reputation: Murdox had among diuers children a yong man to his yongeſt ſonne, of body well proportioned, of face louely, a great company kéeper, giuen much to riot, yea giuen ouer as it proued, ſo that no allowance of his father, nor counſell of his mother preuailed with him: but will was to him a law, no profit ſeemed to him ſo pleaſing as wanton pleaſure: but as one ſinne is father to another, ſo riot be got gréedy deſire of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to maintaine waſt, &amp; this youth (being perſwaded Pets was very rich) on ſunday the 22. of Iune, after his owne Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was rid to Hounſlow, Pets &amp; his wife being at church, entred the houſe, and found a ſonne of Pets about 10. yeres of age in the houſe. The child knowing Murdox, had no feare: albeit Murdox in his ſight had rifled the houſe, &amp; miſſed foure pounds that was tied in the corner of a ſhéete, taking onely a little purſe (as was proued by euidence) wherein fourtéene pence was. Finding no more, he called the boy, Iacke ſaith he, wilt thou not tell? No indéed ſaith the child. Then come and bring a knife quoth Murdox, and wée will into the groue to cut whipſtockes. The ſimple child tooke a knife &amp; follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and beeing come through a cloſe into the groue, hee with the knife the childe brought, gaſht him about the throat but miſt the weaſon, and ſo thinking the childe to bée dead left him, but hearing the boy crie, returned and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him into the right breſt then liſtening againe, he againe returnd and ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him againe: and the third time comming backe, ſtopping the childes mouth with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, hee thinking him ſurely dead, and leauing him, went toward the Church, by which time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 lines">
                     <desc>〈3 lines〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:26357:4"/>
neighbor Petshis. Thether the mother and her eldeſt ſonne went to ſée the cauſe: the yong ſonne would not goe. When Murdox wife came there, they ſaw the houſe rifled, but onely the wofull mother cried for her ſonne, her ſonne. Some neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors ſpied a footing towardes the groue followed it, and found the boy all to be weltred in gore. And perceiuing life to bee in him, two layde him on a cloke, and beetwéene them brought him home. Where murdoxes mother moſt of any other when hee had recouered ſpeech) ſought to haue him tell who did the déed. At laſt with great feare he told, &amp; preſently yong Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox was apprehended, and found bayle, denying the deed with many bitter curſes. That day he careleſly followed his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but the childes conſtancie in his accuſation, made the parents to bring him before the Lord Anderſon, who ſo ſifted him that he confeſſed the fact. For which he was condemned at the Seſſions at newgate, and executed on munday the 14. of Iuly. The mone he made, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gréefe he had of his miſſpent life, too late too helpleſſe was lamentable, but ſuch is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of ryot, where no regard is had of ſpending aboue the courſe of lawful getting, neceſſity muſt néedes follow: games, wantonnes, &amp; eaſe, are not continued without exceſſiue coſt. He died in his prime of youth, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flower of his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, in the blouming of his hopes, making his owne ende ſhamefull by waſtfull ouerſight. The child (by Gods power) is recouered, and at the barre gaue euidence againſt him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>The murder of the Graſier.</head>
               <p>OVr laſt part is compoſed of enuie, Auarice, falſe freend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, murder, maſſacring, and their reward. For enuie. One Dernly a graſier about Eſſex ſide being very familiar with William Randolph a man of his owne profeſſion, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling about Cardiffe, and hauing much dealing about Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don, ſtomacked (as diuers men of one trade doo) the great dealings of Randolph. Randolph ſéemed to be a man of gentle nature
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26357:5"/>
and verye open to his fréend, taking Dernley for no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of his, for Dernley was priuie that Randolph had receiued aboue thrée hundred pound, and was to ride from London through Ailſbury toward Wales. Whereupon he acquainted, one Parry dwelling in Shorditch, and Richardſon another of his confedrats dwelling in Knight-rider ſtréete in London wyth Randolphs condition, charge of money, and the way hee had to ride. They fell in company with Randolph a little from London, and verie curteouſty bare him company to Ailſbury: and by the way one Tailer of Ailſbury chanced among them, and noting by Randolphs talke that hee concealed not his charge of mony, beſides obſeruing how Parrey and Richard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon were horſt, and weaponed, tolde Randolphe ſecretly at his comming to Ailſbury, that hee did not wiſely to ride ſo open, and willed him to looke well to Parrey and Richardſon, for hee miſtruſted them. The good old man beléeuing the faire ſpéeches of the ill intending murderers, better than the honeſt aduiſe of the plaine meaning man, replied, they were very fréendly Gentlemen dwelling in London, ſuch as had vſed him very kindly, and that for a world of wealth he would not haue an euill thought of them, ſo honeſt they ſéemed, ſo gentle, ſo faire conditioned, whereupon Tailer ſéeing Randolphs minde deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed to vſe more words. But this talke of his, either by Randolphs meanes or ſome other courſe came to Parrey and Richardſons hearing, whereupon making ſhew or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, in the morning they went before him out of towne, pretending haſt alſo of their way. Randolph hearing they were gone, greatly blamed the Chamberlaine, and with all ſpéed haſted to poaſt after them, &amp; comming about ſome mile from Ailſburie met one who tolde him two ſuch Gentlemen were eaſely riding not a full mile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. When <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed to miſchance, with what violence doth his euill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> draw him onward. As faſt as horſe could runne he galleys af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to ſome get ſight of them that were readye to him his fight with eternal darkneſſe: when hee was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26357:5"/>
hearted companions, vnder coleur of kinde ſalutation, turning their horſes heades to bid him welcome, Parrey firſt with a Iudas like welcome diſchargd his piſtol in his boſome: with the entrance of the bullet the poore man laid his faint hand on his wounded breſt, while Richardſon with the ſecond bullet ſhot him through hand and belly. So fell he downe, and they like bloodſucking wolues ceaſd on this innocent, dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in his death wound vpon wound, mangling his face with ſuch inhumane cruelty, as no barbarous tirant coulde more outragiouſly haue done. Then drew they him into a thicket, and rifled his dead body: where Richardſon yet vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied with cruelty ſtabd him into the necke, with ſuch vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that in pulling back his hand, the pummell and handle of his dagger cam off, but ſhe blade he left ſticking in his neck, which blade was one witnes againſt the murdrous maiſter. This done, they turnd his horſe into the wood and houer about the country ſome two daies and more after. For it was the ſecond day before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> murdred body was found, by a fellow that ſought cattle. When the hue and cry came to Ailſbury, Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler among other went to ſee the body, and by the apparell bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the face he knew it was the carcaſſe of that wretched man, who had refuſed his counſell at Ailſbury the other night before. He deſcried their apparell, proportions, horſes and all ſuch markes as hee aduiſedly had taken while he rid in their company. To London, toward Wales, &amp; euery way the hue and cry went. Parrey was taken in Wales, and conteſt the fact. Richardſon at his owne doore in London. A while he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the deed, but long he ſtood not in it, both of them accuſed Dernley, and to Ailſbury they are all gone to ſuffer deſera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d death. God giue them repentant hearts ſo lament earneſtly the cruelty of their handes, for w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> more bloodineſſe haue I not heard a murder of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time to be followed. The murdred man as I before ſaid, was plaine, ſimple, &amp; of no miſtruſtfull heart. The murderers to the worlde eye well thought off. Dernley the cauſer of Randolphs death, a very wealthy man eſtéemed of honeſt conuerſation. Parrey and Richardſon the executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26357:6"/>
borne of honeſt parentage, faire conditioned, not thought to liue ſo diſorberly as it ſéemeth they now did. For had they not béen exerciſed to robbery and ſpoyle, howe durſt Dernley haue broke ſo hainous a matter to them, or if he had not before time ſo purpoſt, how could hée ſo ſodainly haue found them for his purpoſe: but the community of the euill hath an euil end, and though they band themſelues for a time together, death gapes for them, &amp; their deſtruction commeth ſodainly. Would ſome by theſe and many more examples would take heed. It is impoſſible murder ſhould be hid, and therefore it is folly for any man to follow it. This brother in law and father in law Graygooſe &amp; wright Murderers of innocent Thomas Cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers, thought that their ſecret miſchiefe could haue been as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly conceiled as wickedly conceiued? but euen the day the dead body was found, their treachery was found: Murdox thought he had made ſure worke with youg Pets, but hee yet liues, whom he cruelly intended to haue ſlaine, and being but a child condemned him a man, before the ſeate of iudgement. Theſe laſt thrée thoght the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues as ſure, but blood cried from the earth, and the voice of the reuenger hath made them trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Looke, looke, ye murderers how many miſeries ye bring to thoſe that liue, by your complotting others deaths: the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, wiues, children, followers of thoſe you murder, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ment you ill, are when your hatefull déede is done, vexing followers of you to your deſerued deaths: your parents wiues children, followers, fréendes mournfull and helpleſſe lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for your amiſſe, your owne names perpetually inrolled among murderers. If you be tempted to any ill, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the end, ſhame miſery and confuſion of face, you that were wont to walke fréely, muſt be led like bondmen, that haue béen wel thought on, muſt bee the peoples wonder: that were fréends ſole comfort, are moſt ſharp percing ſwords vnto their hearts. Let thought of blood be farre from ye, for it is a ſinne God hats, &amp; no man will not pity.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26357:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
